<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Life and death of the incomparable and indefatigable Tory, Redmond ô Hanlyn commonly called Count Hanlyn: in a letter to Mr. R.A. in Dublin.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48408</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828249</idno>
  <idno type="VID">32676</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240881090</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216522</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828249</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99828249e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48408)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32676)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1912:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Life and death of the incomparable and indefatigable Tory, Redmond ô Hanlyn commonly called Count Hanlyn: in a letter to Mr. R.A. in Dublin.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Foster at the Kings-Arms in Skinner-Row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Dublin] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXII. [1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">O'Hanlon, Redmond O'Hanlon, --  Count, d. 1681 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32676:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32676:1"/>
            <p>LIFE and DEATH OF THE Incomparable and Indefatigable TORY, Redmond ô Hanlyn, Commonly Called Count Hanlyn: In a Letter to Mr. <hi>R. A.</hi> in DUBLIN.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>John Foster</hi> at the Kings-Arms in <hi>Skinner-Row,</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:32676:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32676:2"/>
            <head>THE LIFE and DEATH Of Redmond ô Hanlyn &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU have often refreshed me with the Stories and Occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Dublin,</hi> for which I Despair of ever having an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertunity to make a sutable return (this Barren and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Country affording no passages worth the recounting) yet since the Novelty, and singularity of the Ensuing Discourse may possibly afford you some tolerable diversion, you may please to throw a way a few minutes in the reading of it; as I have mispent 2 or 3 houres in the writing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Redmond,</hi> the Son of <hi>Loghlin</hi> ô <hi>Hanlyn,</hi> was Born near to <hi>Pointz-Pass</hi> in the County of <hi>Ardmagh</hi> in the year 1640, the year preced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Last <hi>Irish Rebellion</hi> as if fate had sent him a harbinge to the confution and mischeif following, or as if the birth of so great a man ought to be attended by no less then an universal conflagra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Mother of this Eminent Hero prompted with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural curiosity incident to her Sex, and Melancholick tempers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came very earnest and inquisitive after her future fate, and to that end consulting a fortuneteller one day he thought it good manners to gratifie his Clyent by a pleasing prediction, and so gave her this Oraculous answer, <hi>Sheely</hi> joy make hast and marry for in due sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, thou shalt be mother of a Son who shall Eclips his Family and Kindred; and become the most famous of his time and Nation. This added to the common incentives of Love, Fancy and a longing desire, to have a Mate made the poore Woman Malleble to every im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32676:3"/> and inclined to surrender her fortress to the first agressor, so that it was no great difficulty for seignior <hi>Laughlin</hi> to finde that Lady in the humor, who was predisposed to the intrigue by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of such powerful preparatives, fancying to her self that at least she should be a mother of a young St. <hi>Patrick.</hi> Thus the Amour was lucky and short, his conversation produced an intimate Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity, Courting was Baffled by Wedlock, and from a Matrimonial inoculation sprouted this hopeful Imp, of whom I am now about to give an account.</p>
            <p>His first appearance in the world did administer great cause of wonder and chatt to the assisting Gossips who were surprised to see him sprawling with the Brand of a <hi>Roman</hi> T in his brest, which the Neighbours did in Flatery interpret to portend some great fortune to the Babe; and that the Mark representing a headless Cross he should at least be a Martyr for Christian Religion; but success hath shewn, that it barely denoted a <hi>Thief,</hi> or was a Character to Prognosticate an Eminent <hi>Tory.</hi> I shall omit the passages of his Infancy, in which there appeared very early Bloomings toward the most exquisite Villany, exceeding all his Comerades and Contemporaryes both in the inventive, and the managing part of any Thievish Strategem: none so dextrous at Filching, Nimming and Cheating; none so Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious at hiding, Dissembling, or Excusing, nor so confident at Down-right Lying and denying, the <hi>Spanish Gusmond,</hi> the <hi>French Duval,</hi> and the <hi>English</hi> Rogue, were but Puisnes in the Profession, not worthy to be mentioned in one Calander with our <hi>Irish</hi> Grandee: they owed their proficiency in Wickedness to time, custom, and evil conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereas our Land Picaroon came into the World naturally stord with all sorts of Vice, and from the impulse of his own Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations Commenced a Villain <hi>Paramount,</hi> without being beholding to example or Instruction; and tho some men purchase compassion by attributing their Faults to the persuasion of others, he thought it a disparagement to extenuate his crime by the ordinary apology of a temptation. It was his good fortune to be Educated in his Youth in an <hi>English</hi> Schoole, where he attaind to so complete a perfection in that Language that it might have proved of great advantage to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32676:3"/> him at his Latter end, if he had not sinned beyond the mercy of the Book. Among the Boyes he first practised the Art of Thievery refin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and had so excellent a knack at diving, that he never failed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day to gage the Pockets of them that sat near him, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle them to the Last Cob-nut. At Length success had so hardned him, that with a barefaced Impudence he made the utmost tryal of his Skill, and neatly pickt his Masters Pocket; while he was making the repetition of his weeks task, which being Discovered by one of the Scholars who had often been squeesed by him; he thought it best to retire from under the Dominion of the Ferula, and so first found out the way of being upon his keeping; but his indulgent parents (especially the Mother, how impatiently panted after the great Atchievements of her Son) instead of remanding him to his Study, &amp; the Discipline of the Rod, remitted him to the Dictates of his own will, and gave him his full swing without controle; which he most ingratefully improved so much to their disadvantage, that at the next Rent day there was not so much money to be found in Pocket, or Trunk, as would Discharge the Bayliffs fees: the nimble Youth hath bin there before them, and narrowly ransackt all corners, the most sure and secret repository was not inaccessible to him. Every Lock, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Bolt slew open at the first approch of this incomparable Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier; thus like a good Bird, he pickt out the eyes of them that hatch him, and enriched himself by the utter Ruin of those that reared him. In this Extremity his Friends were reduced to the last shift, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inforced to metamorphose their Cowes into coyn, they did for some time Eat, Drink, and wear Beef, in the mean time the young Count began to know sorrow, seldom meeting with conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient occasions of recruting himself, and exerting his Ingenuity in parloyning; the thin unfrequented Rodes in the Country afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no game worth his attendence, the poore Money less hanters of Villages were no quarry to be stoopt at by this Towring Eagle. Wherefore at a solemn consult held by the friends and Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all sides. It was unanimously resolved, that, to satiate the thirsty ambition of this aspiring <hi>Coesario,</hi> all means and speed should be used to procure some publick Imployment, or place of Trust for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32676:4"/> him; and among all the projects and proposals offered on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, none seemed so conducible to his Honour and Advantage, as to be in the quality of a Pedee to some Gentleman, and so by great Interest, and sharp Solicitation he was admitted a Foot-boy to Sir <hi>George Acheson</hi> a worthy Gentleman, Living in the Neighbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and now it might fairly have bin expected, that being planted in a well ordered Family, the good Instructions of his Master, and the civil example of his fellow servants, might have contributed to the reclayming of his haggard-disposition, and have produced in him a Reformation of his Manners; but his jadish Nature inclined him to be restive, and inflexible; the sparks of vise (which had a while layn smothered under the penitential Ashes of affliction, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and a Dissembled sobriety) began to burst out, and instead of being a single Demoniack, he appear'd to be possessed with a Legion. But as in the habits and exercise of Vertue, and the acquests of Learning and knowledg, thô a man may be famed for an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of good Qualities, yet he is commonly more eminent for one, and guided by his own Genius to the study of some particular Art or Science: so this Monsieur (tho plentifully endowed with all manner of Ludeness, yet) was noted to take most pleasure in cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Stratagems, and sherking Circumventions, seeming to Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate his facultyes that way. Rather for a recreation, than out of necessity; and like a generous Huntsman pursuing his Game, not so much out of greedyness after the Prey, as for love of the sport. Hence it came to pass, that out of a wantoness in sinning, he would usually convay his Masters Horses out of the Stable, and Cowes out of the Closes, and after a few days search and wonder, return them to the place from whence they were taken, making Experiments in in the Trade; that he might become the greater Master; some time he would make a Sally to the Mountains and use means to disburthen the Land from too great a Stock of Cattle; some time he would be picqueiring on the High-way, and examin a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Portmanteau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and graciously ease the Load laid on the poor Sumpter-horse; some time he would visit the Market Towns, and probe the Boxes, and make a privy search into the Warehouses
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32676:4"/> and Sellars, &amp; prune them from some superfluous commodities; at one Fair you should find him the best furnished Chapmen, selling all sorts of ware; at another you should meet him bidding at all bargains and liberally Strewing his Money amongst the people; using daily to practise the Art of Disguising and extremely delighting himself in the reflection upon his variety of shapes and postures; Thus he passed some years in great satisfaction, and Impunity, but at last he was by an odd Accident detected, being one day challenged for a stolen Horse, which he exposed to sale in a publick Fair, and confidently avow'd to belong to his Master, but the owner giving a suddain twitch to his Tayl, pulled away the artificial besome, which onely had accused him and so discovered the Cheat. <hi>Hanlyn</hi> seemed equally to admire the chance, and pretended to fetch the Groom, who should justifie the property of the Horse, but by that means he escaped thro the Crowd, and never returned to the Fair to justify his Possession, nor to his Master, to give an account of his Loss. Now it concerned him to play his Master-Game, and either to live Incognito in a nother Country, or curiously to masque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade it in his own. Of all the expedients that presented to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, he thought it the most proper to become a Servant to a <hi>Fanatick Teacher</hi> (as to whom it is no strange thing to play the Counterfit) and so avoiding the Inquiry of the orthodox Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, who would not look for him in such places, and being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the danger that might arise from the Trechery, or weakness of the men of his own Religion and country, he was safe enough among the Brethren, tho he should come to be known, and secure against all Plots, and Attempts, being inlisted in that Fraternity, some say that the greatest Design he had in picking up his new Master, was to Improve himself in the mistery of Disguising; for tho he very well knew the utmost could be done by changing of Cloaths, Perukes and Company, yet he was but a novice in the natural way of doing it, by distorteng the Countnance, and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wry faces, and for as much as his new Master did in that knack out do all the Mountebanks and Players, he made himself sure of acquiring the Art, by hearing his Master hold forth but
<pb facs="tcp:32676:5"/> five or six Long Sermons; The Master taking Notice of the pregnant Ingenuity of his Servant, and how neatly he could Act, and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him in his Pulpit Postures, preferred him to be Clerk to the Congregation; and he having naturally a strong and clear voice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came so excellent at tuning of a Psalm, (twanging it out with a right <hi>Geneva Trillo</hi>) that the Brethren admired him for his good Gifts, and the Sisters were enamourd of his great abilitys. In this posture continued he, till the Happy Restoration of his Majesty; and then, in imitation of the General Act of Oblivion, all people were will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to pass by his former backslidings, and so Mr. <hi>Hanlyn</hi> returned to his Country; but put on the most false, and dangerous of all his Disguisses, the pretence and appearance of an honest man. The first Imployment he imbarqued in, after the expiration of Anarchy, was to be a Collector of <hi>Pole-money,</hi> wherein he Demened himself without the Noyse of any Scandal, fairly discharging himself from the publick receiver, tho with the general Squeesing, and over reaching of the poore Country people. A while after we find him a Farmer and Receiver of Harth-Mony (an undertaking that has proved fatal to every man that has been so concerned!) wherein being unsuccessful, and not able by all industry to stretch his Receipts equal to his Contract, he began to grow pensive, afterwards care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, and at last desparate. But as Hunting is commended as the most proper exercise for young men, whose Birth &amp; metal may cherish in them a hope of being in time Generals, and great Commanders: so those two Imployments of <hi>Pole-Money</hi> &amp; <hi>Hearth-mony</hi> did certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enable this <hi>Knight-Errant</hi> to get an exact knowledg of every high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, Village, House, and Person, &amp; consequently to become the most notorious in that Damnable Profession of Padding, and for so many years to escape, in spight of all the endeavors and devices used to entrap him; the credit of being a Publican, &amp; the Reputation of his good Clark-like Qualities, had rendred him tolerably well esteemed, and procured him the consent of a Neighbour, to give his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to him in Marriage; with a prety considerable Portion! which his Necessityes forcing him to misapply, to salve the deficiencyes of his Publick bargains; he had now no Retreat, but to his wits,
<pb facs="tcp:32676:5"/> and to rowse up those Dormant vices which so long a desnetude, and deviation to the Path of Vertue had chilled, and almost extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished. About this time his Creditors began to dun him, his Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to torment him, his Bonds were sued, and Execution ready to be served on his Bayl, and himself reduced to this uneasy Dilemma, either to submit to the Law by a Voluntary abandoning of Liberty, or to go out of the protection of it, by injoying a dishonourable freedom. Just in the Nick, when he despaird of ever arriving at a Capacity to discharge his Engagements, impartial Death (the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falliable cure of the diseased, and certain Releif of the afflicted) cancelled the greatest, and most troublesome of all his obligations, by whisting of his Wife back to her first principles: whose Obsequies being solemnised by the Barbarious custom of Drinking, and How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, our <hi>Irish Robin-Hood</hi> found himself much more in a fitness to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for himself, having no other to provide for, and determining <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a kind of forced coshering, he shifted his Quarters twice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> without a noise of Drum, or Trumpet, it was not long b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore some of his trusty Centinels gave him Intelligence of an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of advantaging himself by a project very odd, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usual. A certain Theif went into the County of <hi>Meath,</hi> and there Stole two good Horses from one Mr. <hi>Pakenham,</hi> and secretly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed them into the County where <hi>Hanlyn</hi> then Skulked; he as Lord of the Mountains, Assuming to himself a Priviledg in all Estrays, and stoln goods, found a way to steal the same Horses from the Possession of the Theif, and openly owned them, no way fearing that the true Owner would track them to such a Distance, and well knowing that there was no Danger of the Avowry, or Challenge of the last Proprietor: but Mr. <hi>Pakenham</hi> using diligence, and giving timely notice of the Stealth to his friends in several Countys, it fortuned, that the Horses were discovered, and a complaint made to the next Justice of the Peace, and an account given where, and in whose custody they were: whereupon a Warrant was Issued for the apprehending <hi>Redmond,</hi> and securing the Horses; but he unwill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to part with his purchase, resolved to keep them against Gages &amp; Pledges, &amp; so eloigning &amp; removing them from place to place, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated
<pb facs="tcp:32676:6"/> the endeavors of his Prosecutors, and tir'd their Patience. It fortuned that about this time <hi>Loghlin ö Hanlyn,</hi> a Kinsman of his, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing warmly pursued for a Stealth, betook himself to the Mountains, where in a very short time (Birds of one Feather will assemble from the Extremest Parts of the Wood) he mett with <hi>Redmond;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter some time spent in recounting their Adventures, they entred into an Offensive and Defensive League, against the King, the Lawes, and all honest People; and for an inviolable assurance of this Stipulation, <hi>Loughlin</hi> gave his Sister to <hi>Redmond</hi> in Marriage, and he right nobly settled a plentiful Joynture upon her, to be Levyed of all his Neighbours Estates, &amp; Tenants, at his will &amp; Pleasure; <hi>Redmond</hi> was inclined to live a quiet and unactive Life, and to pass his time in shifting &amp; absconding; <hi>Loghlin</hi> being of a more firey &amp; ravening Disposition, enclined wholly to action, and continually solicited his Brother to take the Company, and to go upon their keeping: many arguments were used on both sides, but at last Nature turned the Scale, and <hi>Redmond</hi> consented to Estrange himself from the sight of people, but would not at present yeild to enter into an open Profession of Robery. That which principally moved him to demurr in this resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was, an itching humor he inherited from his Mother, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the course of future Events. To this end he diligenly inquired out the renown'd man of Art, who had foretold something of him before; and with a good see obliged him to cast the Scheme of his Nativity, and resolve him, what would be his Progress, and end: the Learned Southsayer putting on his Conjuring Face, and drawing many Lines and Circles, dappled with Figures and signs of the Planets, at last presented him with this ambiguous Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: <hi>Thou Son of Fortune, and Darling of Fame, thy enterprises shall be great, and thy Success Ʋnparalled; thy Hazards numerous; and thy Escapes miraculous, thy Army shall be small, but thy command great, thy Territory not vast, but thy Revenue unlimitted, thou shalt live without a House, and yet dye in a Bed, the hand of Justice shall not reach thee, neither shalt thou be a Victim to the Law, thou shalt ly in State after thou art dead; and be Bury'd in two several places in one day; thou shalt dy among thy friends, and thy Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes shall not see thy Head.</hi> The Rover was so tickled with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32676:6"/> this Encouraging presage (which he Literally beleived, and alto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether interpreted in his own Favour) especially his Impunity, and Protection from the Gallows; that he resolved immediatly to be it Action, and began to furnish himself with good Armes, nimbl<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Companions, and exquisite Spyes. But whether the conceit of hi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> good fortune had blinded him, or want of experience had made him less circumspect, before he accomplished any great thing, he was sur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prised by a Warrant for the Stol Horses before mentioned, and committed to the Gaol of <hi>Ardmagh,</hi> where certainly he had danced in a Rope, if he had continued till next Assises, but thô his heel<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> were fast, his wits were at liberty, and casting about which way to make an Escape, he at Last pitched upon this Invention. Ther<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> was a youth of his Name and Family, that attented him in th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Gaol, and had Liberty to go to and fro, and serve him with provi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sions: him he intrusted to be very serviceable and obsequious to th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Keeper of the Prison, to wait on him diligently till he Went to Bed and to observe in what Place he Layd the Keys of the Prison every Night, the cunning Boy plaid his part very dextrously; and craftilly insinuated himself into the favour of the Gaoler, and observing that when he had lock'd the several Doors of the Prison, he lay'd the Keys upon a shelf in his own Chamber, he advertised his Master o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> it; who presently laid hold of the opportunity, and the next nigh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> having plyed the Gaoler with good store of <hi>Brandy,</hi> and enabled him to sleep soundly, the nimble Boy went directly to the shelf wher<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Bundle of keys was lay'd, and coming to the cell where his Maste<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> lay, open'd the doors, and released him; and so quietly in the dead of the Night they marched out, Locked the Gate of the Prison, and carried the keys with them. To tell you the fright and consterna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the Gaoler (when he arose in the morning and missed hi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> keys, found <hi>Hanlyns</hi> doore open, and the Prison doore lock'd <hi>Hanlyn</hi> at Liberty, and himself a Prisoner) the Alarm in the Town and the Rumors in the Country, is altogether needless. The Bird was no sooner got out of the Cage, but he fled to the Mountains and before he was mist, was past all possibility of catching. And now having doubled his Crime by breaking of Prison, and desparing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32676:7"/> of mercy or pardon; he resolved to abandon himself to all Lewdness, and to become a perfect bird of Prey. His first care was to provide himself with a good Horse, and Armes, and to that purpose ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving intelligence that a person in the Country had a very good Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in his Stable, he resolved to have him, and to effect it he used this Stratagem; mounting upon an ordinary Garran, clad in a long Frize-Coat, without a Sword, or any other Arms, he came to the Parsons House, and desiring to speak with him, he told him, that having heard that he had a good flock of sheep, he would willingly buy a score of fat wethers; and the price being soon agreed on, the person and his Chapman began to be very great, and concluding the bargain and the day with a merry Glass, Mr. <hi>Hanlyn</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted to his apartment, and getting up very early next morning, he went to the Stable; and with great confidence bid the Groom to put his Saddle on his Masters Gelding, that he might ride him to the water, they having made a Bargain for him upon lik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; the Groom no way suspecting the new guest, sadled the horse, and <hi>Hanlyn</hi> got upon him, rid fair and softly away, and liked his Bargain so well, that he never returned to finish, or find fault with <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t. And now being very well mounted, he began to project how to be furnished with good Armes, and calling to mind, that he had often seen such things in a Gentlemans House, whom formerly he used to visit, and who by Living in a secure place, was the less secure, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arms to guard his House, but appointing no body to guard his Arms, he formed this Design. He writ a Letter to his brother <hi>Logh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> and subscribed it with his own Name, intimating a purpose to Rob a certain house within two or three Nights, and appointing him to meet in such a wood, in order to it; this Letter he purposely dropt in the High way, and then directed <hi>Edmond</hi> ô <hi>Hanlyn,</hi> one of his trusty Guard, to take it up, and to carry it presently to the Gentleman, whose Arms he gaped for, pretending himself to be a Countryman that had bin robbed by <hi>Hanlyn;</hi> and undertaking, with the help of another man, and Arm'd with a couple of the best Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, to bring <hi>Hanlyn</hi> Dead or a Live; the Gentleman to easily and credulously (and for that reason I will not name him) complyed with the Proposal and appointing a Lusty active fellow to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32676:7"/>
               <hi>Edmond,</hi> he gave them his two best Guns; <hi>Edmond</hi> proved so good a spy, that early next morning he found out <hi>Redmond</hi> indeed, but delivered up his Carbine to him, And the other man, to save his life, was forced to follow his leader. After this, not one day passed, wherein he did not committ some Robbery, either in the County of <hi>Down, Ardmagh</hi> or <hi>Monaghan,</hi> and by exquisit projections, secret Provision &amp; quick executing, he gather'd a great mass of mony, horded up a considerable Magazine of Arms, &amp; became not onely ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to Travellors, and House keepers, but troubled and tyred many Parties of the Army, who continually pursued him from place to place, &amp; he as constantly &amp; miraculously still made an escape. If I should enumerate his several Adventures, I should turn this Letter into a Treatise; I will onely single out three or four of them, and come to the conclusion of them, and this paper. He observed that the foot-soldiers were his most dangerous Persecutors, and that there Red-Coats were a sufficient Pass to them in all places, and a Barr against all suspition; wherefore to gratify his Revenge, and promote his own security, he resolved by some knack to get some of them, and thus he brought it to pass: upon the Mountain between <hi>Newry</hi> and <hi>Dundalk</hi> there was a small Cabbin reared, and a File of men appointed to keep Guard there, and secure the Road; <hi>Hanlyn</hi> in a dark night plants himself, with ten of his Followers, near to the Guard-house, but under cover of a Little Hill, and in the morning slipping into the High-way, they came on as travellers, and while some of them entertained the Centinel with discourses, and questions about the way, the rest slipt in and surprised the Guard; whom having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently removed to an obscure place, and bound them fast, one of the Number was left to watch them while <hi>Honlyn</hi> and the rest clad them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in their Red Coats, and so stayed as a Guard, and in all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance as the Soldiers of the Army; that day very many persons went on the Road, upon accasion of a Fair that was kept therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and every man as he passed by was taken into the Guard-house; rifled of his Horse, Armes, Clothes and Money, and so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd under the Hill, and there kept till Night, that they might not tell tales, or make any Discovery. It is incredible to relate, with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32676:8"/> what ease, and success he continued his Trade of Robbing by the opportunity of these Red-Coats, Skipping from one side of the Country to the other, and men that saw them, instead of avoyding went directly to them, where expecting assistance and a Convoy, they were snapt by those Counterfeits and catched in a toyl. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the <hi>Count</hi> would put on a good suit, and appear on the Road like a Gentleman, his man riding along with him with a Portman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and one day being in that Posture, he overtook a poor man Stript to his Shirt, and mightily Lamenting his Misfortune, and inquiring what the matter was, the man told him that a little while agon he was Robbed by <hi>Hanlyn,</hi> and a Horse Loaded with goods taken from him. <hi>Hanlyn</hi> (suspecting that either some of his own Crew did play the Free-bouters, or some of the Country did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to Act in his Name, tho without his Commission) inquired which way the thief went, and bidding the man to follow him, he went, Speedily on the Track, &amp; in a short time overtook him, whom having soundly beaten, he restored to the poor man the goods that were taken from him, with some thing of the Thieves for Interest, then piniond the Fellow, &amp; deliverd him to the plunder'd man, together with a Mittimus to the Gaol of <hi>Ardmagh,</hi> which was penned to the effect; <hi>Redmond</hi> ô <hi>Hanlyn, none of his Majesties Justices of the Peace, but Chief Ranger of the Mountains, to the keeper of the Gaol in</hi> Ardmagh. <hi>I command you to take this fellow into your custody for Robbing in my Quarters, without my License, there to remain till he be hanged for a Thief, and Quarter'd for a Cheat:</hi> The Gaoler was hugely puzled how to behave himself in the Case, but being advised by his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, he thought it best to detain him for a great Rogue, tho trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him by a greater, and at the next Assises he was hanged for the Robbery. A while after <hi>Hanlyn</hi> having gently equipped him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self and three servants (which he could easily do, having robbed Pedlars, and Shop-keepers, as well as Houses) himself clad in a Modish Garb, with a new Peruke, and a rich Belt. His valet in handsome apparel, his Groom and Lackey in a Rich Livery, with his led Horse and Sumpture, travelled the Road and very orderly came
<pb facs="tcp:32676:8"/> to <hi>Ardmagh,</hi> and took up the best Inn in the Town, where he solaced himself with the best meat, and Wine the Place afforded, and in the morning sent to the Lieutenant who commanded the party that then <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ay in Town, to accomodate him with a Guard to convey him over the <hi>Fews,</hi> who accordingly sent him four Horse-men to attend him, and away they went; when they were come near to <hi>Dundalk, Hanlyn</hi> made a stop at a certain place between two Hills; i<gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n a thicket of scrubby wood, and having thanked the Horse-men for their pains, he gave each of them a <hi>Dollar;</hi> they in requital discharged every man his Pistole; and he as generously gave them again as much as before; the Soldiers scorning to be behind with him in Civility, discharging the other Pistol; then <hi>Hanlyn</hi> seeming to be well pleas'd with these gratulatory Vollyes, Desired them to fire once more, but perceiving that they Look'd one upon the other &amp;, had not as much Powder among them, as would charge their Pistols agen, he whistled &amp; presently came in a swarm of his Mountaneers, who gently seased on the Troopers, took back the Money, and disarmed them; and <hi>Hanlyn</hi> giving them thanks for their convoy, fairly dismissed them. One day <hi>Hanlyn</hi> went among his Friends and Contributers to visit them, and finding them in great Trouble and Confusion, demanded the reason; they told him, that the Receiver of their Land-Lords Rent, was newly gone from them, &amp; had carry'd away all their Cows for a Distress: he ask'd them how much mony was due, which when he understood, he very nobly Lent them the money, and bid them follow the Receiver presently, and redeem their Cows; the poor people went in all hast, and overtook the man, and payed them oney, and brought back their Cows; <hi>Hanlyn</hi> follow'd at a distance, and perceiving the Cows restored to the Owners, he spurs up to the the Receiver, and told him, he must presently refund the Money he had borrowed from his Quarters, which he was glad to do, and went away without a Penny in his Purse. About this time certain resolute Persons of the Country Determining to pursue <hi>Hanlyn</hi> night and day, till they might apprehend him, Set out in the evening, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding themselves into Small parties to avoyd suspicion, appointed a Rendezvous in the morning, and that night went to repose in several
<pb facs="tcp:32676:9"/> Little Cabbins in the Mountains; <hi>Hanlyn</hi> got Intelligence of it, and hearing where four of the principal men had taken up their Quarters, and had bespoke as swild mutton for their Supper, he came with his Party, and Just as they were going to eat, rushed in upon them; and surprised them; and then very bravely he and his Company sat down to supper, making the Country-men wait at their Backs, and when they had done, he bid the man of the House to take his servans to supper, but charged him for his Life not to give them a Bitt, but what was left at his Table, and so about Mid-night, taking away their Arms, and their best Cloaths, he went off, desiring the Country-men to mind their Husbandry hereafter, and not to imploy themselves in Hunting. The Report of this, as it discouraged the Country men, so it inflamed the Soldiers to persecute him, &amp; to endeavour to catch this Slippery Eele: thereupon it was agreed, that the several Parties from several Garrisons should set out at one time, and scower the Mountains, and search all suspected places: this design did put <hi>Hanlyn</hi> to his Trumps, for being ferreted out of his Hole ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> night, he was forced next day to trust to the speed of his Horse, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to be in continual motion, but the Alarum grew so hot, and the pursuit so close after him, that being Imbost, he had no way but to dodg, and give them the Go-by; he espy'd an <hi>English House</hi> not farr from the Road, and thither he hasted, and alighting confidently at the Gate, desired to speak with the Gentleman of the House, who civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly saluting him, <hi>Hanlin</hi> with great Assurance told him, that he Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a Party in Chase of the famous <hi>Tory Hanlin,</hi> that they had rid all night, and in the dark he had lost his Company, and being almost faint with hunger and travell, he begg'd the favor of him to suffer him to take an Hours Repose in his house, and withall intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, that if in the mean time the Party shud come that way, he might not be awakened, only that he woud inquire what Road they took, and he woud soon overtake them: the Gentlemen seeing him in the Garb of a Soldier, himself and Horse Dirty and tyred, gave Credit to what he said, and Lock'd him up in a Chamber; within a few minutes the Party came to the door, and calling for a Little Drink told the Gentleman they were pursuing <hi>Hanlyn,</hi> and hoped in
<pb facs="tcp:32676:9"/> a Little time to overtake him, and so went on their Course; <hi>Hanlin</hi> was not in a case to sleep, but overheard the Discourse, and alleging that he had rested sufficiently, he came forth pretending an impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to get up to his Company, and thanking the Gentleman for his kindness (as he had very great Reason) he galop'd away, but quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forsook the Road he was directed to, and posted back to his old Quarters, which the Souldiers had in vain searched. This perillous and unexpected <hi>Attaque</hi> put such a fright on <hi>Hanlins</hi> principall A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors, that knowing they were detected, and fearing to be clapt up for Harborers, they resolved to adventure head and pluck with their Leader, and openly to rob and spoil with him: <hi>General Hanlyn</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering, that naked and unarm'd men would contribute Little to his advantage, began to cast about how to procure supplyes for them, &amp; partly out of Experience how convenient it was, and partly out of Revenge to the Souldiers, who so Lately had driven him to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremest shift, he determined with himself to find out some knack to purchase some more Red-Cotes, and his subtil Genius soon prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to this Exploit. In an old stump of a Castle between <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalk</hi> and <hi>Newry,</hi> two Files of men were quartred to secure the Rode, <hi>Hanlyn</hi> understanding that it was the Custom of the Soldiers twice a week in the day time to go abroad to gather sticks and Heath, for firing, Leaving onely one man to be a Centinel, carefully watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his oppertunity, and with six of his followers came up sudainly to the place and surprised the Centinel, whom he ty'd, and clapt into a corner, reliving his Guard with one of his own men, clad with the Soldiers Coat, and set in the same place and posture; anon one of the Souldiers returns with a burden of Sticks, and entering at the door, was soon secur'd by those within, and Lay'd up with his Comrade; a little while after came another, and was served in the same manner, and in two hours time they were every one tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan'd, and made Prisoners in their own Fort, <hi>Hanlyn</hi> suplying each vacancy with a Recruit of his own men; and having that day Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every Traveller that past by, (who expected no such Treatment in that place, and from men in Red-Coats) he removed his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Night, carrying with him his Prey of all sorts. And
<pb facs="tcp:32676:10"/> now the Gentleman began to grow formidable, no house less than a Fortress, was secure against his Attempts; no Convoy less then a Troop or Company, was sufficient to protect Travellers, the Noyse of it fill'd, <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the News and Fame spred into forein Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes (insomuch as the Frenchman in his Gazet gave him the Title of <hi>Count-Hanlyn</hi>) so that his Grace the Lord Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland</hi> (who had used all manner of care and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spection Imaginable placing Horse and Foot in every Town and Garrison within the Counties of <hi>Ardmagh, Down</hi> and <hi>Monaghan,</hi> setting a price upon his Head, &amp; assuring a very considerable Reward, to him that should bring him in Alive or Dead) thought it necessary to use some extraordinary Address to clense the Land from this growing Swarm of Vermin, and to that end he gave a Commission to Captain <hi>Trevor Lloyd</hi> to draw out from the Garrisons such Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Horse and Foot as he thought requisite, and with them to pursue the <hi>Toryes</hi> Night and Day, and give them no Rest: Captain <hi>Lloyd</hi> observed his Instructions with all possible diligence and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and did intercept and distroy several of <hi>Hanlyns</hi> Followers, but such was the subti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity and care of <hi>Count-Hanlyn,</hi> that by no means nor inventions he could be surprised, but the Captain command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing several Parties of Horse and Foot from all sides of the Country, and inviting the Country men to come unto the chase, they unken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel'd the Fox, and pursued him so closely from one Mountain to another, that the poor <hi>Count</hi> was driven to the Sea-side near to <hi>Carlingford</hi> Where by his Wits he defected the Industry of a Little Army; for perceving a small Boat near to the shore; he rode fair and softly toward it, and then abondoning his Horse and Arms, he call'd to the Boat man, and told him that he Was a sickly man, and advised by his Physitian, to go two or three Leagues into the Sea, and if he would Row him out of the Harbor, to try if he could be Sea-Sick for an Hour or two, he would give him ten shillings for his pains; the poor Boat man was overjoy'd at the proffer, and quickly computing what an Advantage it was to gain that by an Hours work, which a weeks toyl in fishing would hardly have advanced, he admitted the <hi>Count</hi> into his Boat, and row'd out from the shore,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32676:10"/> which they had not long forsaken, before the <hi>Count</hi> could perceive a multiude of men coming down from the Mountains, whom he well knew to be his Persecutors: and fearing that another Boat might be procured to follow his, he spok to the skipper to row with all hast to the other side of the Head land, which the poor man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unwilling to do (Least the wind might drive him into the main Sea) the <hi>Count</hi> took out his Pocket Pistol, and with a thundring Oath assured him, that if he did not presently obey him, he shoud ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver return to Land: the poor man was forced to comply, and the <hi>Count</hi> vouchsafing to put his hand to an Oar, in a short time they were got quit out of sight, and then rowing two and fro under cover of the High Land all the day, they came at Night into a little Creek, and the <hi>Count</hi> having Nobly paid for his passage, traveled thro by ways, and got safe to the house of one of his Harborers. After this the <hi>Count</hi> began to think it the most advisable course, wholy to abscond himself: at least for some time; and so using means to have his late Adventure with the Fisherman published, he caused it to be given out, that he and the Boat man were gon into <hi>Scotland;</hi> which Rumor going for a while current; and he no where head of, nor any Robbery committed thereabout, all endeavors for the taking him were suspended, and he remain'd secure under the Protection of that Mistake. But whether the humor of Robbing were grown connatural to him, or whether his Revenue was Exhausted, and he obliged by Necessity to seek for a Recruit, before six Months were expired, he appeared again on the High ways, to the great detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of many Travellers, who supposing him dead, or in Exile, were too sensibly convinced of their Error. Among the rest, a certain wary Person residing in <hi>Dublin,</hi> had occasion to remit a hundred Pound to a Correspondet in the <hi>North;</hi> and calculating the Charge of it, he considered, that to send it by Bill of Exchange would be to his Damage, and in Bulk of Silver it might gall his Horse, or tempt a tame Tory to make an experiment, and therefore in this Vacation from <hi>Hanlyn,</hi> the safest and cheapest way was to convert the mony into Guinyes, and to quilt it in an old saddle, and send it by a ragged boy, whose poverty and meanness would supersede all suspision,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32676:11"/> and be a sufficient convoy for him, thus Auarice prevailed, and the Boy upon a Lean ill-favourd Garran, with Equipage at all points sutable, set forward on his Journy, and the second night alighted at an Inn, where <hi>Count Hanlyn</hi> had a little before taken up his Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, habited Like a Farmer, and bound to <hi>Dublin</hi> to sell Oatmeal &amp; Griss: the <hi>Count</hi> did no way covet to converse with strange faces, but apprehending no Danger from such an ill accouter'd novice, he hoped by the Inquiry after News, and the state of Affairs in <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> to be a little instructed what future Measures to take so by the help of the Tapster, the two Travellers met, and after general salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations sat down, to initiate their acquaintance by a Pot of Ale: the youth (accustomed to no Liquer in his Masters House, but Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gut) began to suck down the Ale very greedily, which the <hi>Count</hi> observing, having no other design upon him, but to sport himself with his Frailty, began to ply him with cups, interposing now and then a Tuskin of <hi>Brandy,</hi> which in a short time made the Lad to become very talkative, and unlock the secrets of his Heart: the <hi>Count</hi> asked him, if he were not afraid to travel alone, least <hi>Hanlyn</hi> or some of his followers might mett him; no says the other, we hear in <hi>Dublin</hi> that he is gon for <hi>Scotland,</hi> but if he did meet me, he he would not meddle with such a poor thing as I am; perhaps, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py'd the <hi>Count,</hi> he might have a mind to your Horse, or your saddle; my saddle quoth the youth (falling into a Laughter) indeed I may tell you as a freind, my saddle, as mean as it appears, might make a Furniture for my Lord Mayor of <hi>Dublin;</hi> how can that be, says the <hi>Count,</hi> and with that embraced the youth very affectionatly, and promised him everlasting frendship: well, says the Lad, if you will for fear of the worst, promise to go with me as far as <hi>Antrim,</hi> I will tell you the secret; the <hi>Count</hi> assured him he would accompany him, and the other presently told him what a rich Mine was lodged under that barren Cover, and how by that dissimulation he project<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to elude the attempts of all Robbers, the <hi>Count</hi> having so good a Prey almost in his Clutches, call'd for more Drink, and generously pay'd all the Reckoning, and made the Traveller his Bedfellow: in the morning they pursu'd their Journey, the <hi>Count</hi> was not onely
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32676:11"/> his companion, but his Guide, and pretending to Lead him a shorter way cross the Mountains, in a convenient place for the purpose he made a Stand, and told his Fellow-Traveller that he was mightily troubled with the Piles, and that his own Saddle being very hard, he must needs change with his; the poore youth was much dismay'd, and wonder'd what he meant; but the <hi>Count</hi> soon undeceived him, and ingeniously discovering to him who he was, very nobly he gave him a handsom Pad made of green Velvet, for his old Saddle cover'd with Calve skin. The <hi>Count</hi> having now got some Pay into his hands, resolved to rally some of his scatter'd Regiment, and to make one Essay more at his old Trade, and finding that there was no Hopes to obtain a Pardon, or Protection, he purposed to take a desperate Course, and to make war with all mankind; sparing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>her Poor nor Rich, House-keeper, Traveller, Red-Coat or Mantle, and to take their Lives who made Resistance, and would not part with their money. Very numerous, and very strange were the Rapines, and mischiefs that he committed, and as many and as won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful were his Escapes, which in pity to your Patience, I will pass over, and onely mention; that one day a Horse-man riding over <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>he Fews &amp; a Citizen of <hi>Dublin</hi> with him, <hi>Hanlyn</hi> and four more, set <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>pon them; the Torys discharged their Carbines at them, and the Trooper very bravely came up to <hi>Hanlyn,</hi> shot at him with his Blunderbuss, and killed his Horse, and the <hi>Count</hi> falling under <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>im; the rest fled, the Trooper thinking him safe, pursued the rest, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>aving his fellow-Traveller to make all sure by cutting off his Head, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ut the Citizen either fearing to approach a sleeping <hi>Lyon,</hi> or <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>isdaining to mangle a dead Carcass (for the <hi>Count</hi> lay all the while <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ke a man slayn) Jogged on after the Trooper, and the <hi>Count</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>bserving it, made a shift to draw away his Leg from under the Horse, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eaving his Boot behind him, and not regarding the Contest be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ween Love and Honor, slipt out of the way, and soon squatted, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eyond all possibility of a Retrieve; Now many Projects were set on <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>oot, and many Proposals made to the Lord Lieutenant for the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>estruction of this Arch Rebel, which his Grace did encourage and Countenance, (<hi>Ireland</hi> must alway be indebted for its Peace, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity
<pb facs="tcp:32676:12"/> to that most Noble person) but considering in his great Wisdom, that open force, and Soldiers, and publick Pursuit was no probable was to catch him, he pitch'd upon a Gentleman in the Country, who by Foster Kindred was related to the Count tho somewhat remote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, assuring him of very great favour, if he could hansomly bring the Business to effect: The Gentleman undertook the Task, and mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it very discreetly, but with such exact secrecy, that what Arts and Method he us'd to accomplish the Design, is only knowen to himself it may suffice us to hear, and report, that sometime in the Month of <hi>April</hi> Last, <hi>Count Hanlin</hi> growing half distracted with Jelousie, Fear, and suspicion, changing his Quarter every night, &amp; his Guard every day, it came to the Turn of <hi>Art</hi> o <hi>Hanlin,</hi> and <hi>William</hi> ô <hi>Sheal</hi> to be upon the watch the Latter stood on a hill cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinel-perdu, the former attended his Person in his Chamber, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Midnight, when the Count was fast asleep, <hi>Art O Hanlyn,</hi> with his cockt Carabin approched to the Bed where his Cosin, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman Lay; and pour'd the shot into his Brest, and immediately sprang out at the Door, and made with all speed to the next Village <hi>William O Sheal</hi> hearing the shot, forsook his Post, and came run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Room, where he found his Master and Commander weltring in his Blood, who with a faint voice told him, that the Rogue <hi>Art</hi> had kill'd him: &amp; then with a Roman resolution begg'd one favour of him (which he hoped he would not deny to his dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Freind) that he would presently draw his Sword, and cut off his Head, and bury it in some Bog, that his Enemies might not have the satisfaction to dishonor his Family, by advancing it on a Pole; the poore Villan had yet so much Humanity, that he protested he would not touch him for all <hi>Ireland,</hi> the <hi>Count</hi> repeted his Request as earnestly as he could utter it, and the other as obstinately refused, yet promising to do it if he were near him, when he was dead; but the Dispute was soon ended, the <hi>Count Expiring</hi> before he had time to make his will; the man immediatly made him shorter by the Head, and escaped with it. In the morning the News flying thro the Country, a Party came, and carryed his Body to <hi>Newry,</hi> where his Dead Trunk was exposed in a kind of Mock state to the view of all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32676:12"/> People, for the space of three days. So fell the Famous <hi>Hanlin,</hi> and with him the seminary of the <hi>Toryes</hi> was extinguished.</p>
            <p>He was a well timber'd man, tho not of the best Proportion; of Stature indifferently tall; his Body rather nimble, than strong; more subtil, then Valiant; naturally bold but not cruel, sheding no mans Blood out of wantonness, or delight, but in his own defence, or by the Chance of a shot; he was rapacious, but not covetous; he gather'd much money to save himself, and to inrich others; like a Bird of Prey, he was greedy to devour, but all went thro him as fast as he swallowed; had his Inclinations been vertuous, as his Parts were quick, he might have proved a good Subject to his King, and servicable to his Country; Necessity first prompted him to evil courses, and success hardned him in them, he did not rob to mantein his own prodiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, but to gratify his spyes, and pensioners: Temperance, Liberality and Reservedness were the three qualityes that preserved him; none but they of the House where he was, Knew till the next morning where he lay all night; he allowed his followers to stuff themselves with meat and good Liquor, but confined himself to milk and water; he thought it better thrift to disperse his money among his Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Intelligencers, then to carry it in a purse, or hide it in a hole; he prolonged his life by a general distrust, and lost it by a particular credulity; he owed his prosperity to a vicious fidelity, &amp; was brought to distruction by a vertuous Trechery; for others he lived too Long, and for himself he dy'd too soon: by his example let all men beware of growing gradually wicked; let no man presume to commit great crimes in despaire of a pardon for small faults: may he be the last of the Kings Enemies, or all his Enemies be, as he is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have now recreated my self and tryed you; possibly I might have exercised my Fancy on a more profitable Subject and without doubt, another Pen would have performed this more commendably. I need not give you Caution not <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o make it pubilck, Discre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion will restrein you from recommending that to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>thers, in which your own Judgment will check you for taking any delight. But if any other Eye shall chance to peruse it, let me oblidge you to conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l my Name, that no Occasion may be g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ven to censure or Laugh at.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>your Aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctionate Servant.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>August the</hi> 1st. 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:32676:13"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page: 3: l: 35: for Malleble r: Malleable. p: 4: l: 23: for Gusmand r: Gusman p: 5: l: 12: for how r. who l: 18: for hath r: had: p: 7: l: 2: for Chapmen r: Chapman: l: 12: for accused r: amused. p:<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 20: for all Industry r: all his Industry: p: 9: l: 17: for a r: the: p: 10: l: 15: for Company r: Campaign p: 11: l: 13: for intrusted r: instructed: p: 13: l: 7: for Provision r: proceeding, same l: for Executing r. execution l: 14: for them r: him: p: 14: l: 3: for and r: while: p: 15: l: 12: for discharging r: discharged l: 26: for them oney r: the money: p: 16: l: 14: dele the.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32676:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>